Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 33: Complications of the Term Newborn.
Respiratory Distress Neonatal Encephalopathy And Cerebral Palsy Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome Hematological Disorders Newborn Injuries References Term newborns are susceptible to various illnesses and injuries.
In many instances, clinical manifestations of these disorders are extensions of pathological effects already incurred by the fetus.
A common example is the newborn who is depressed and acidotic because of intrapartum septicemia.
Susceptibility varies depending upon gestational age, and those more common in term newborns are considered here.
Those more frequent in preterm neonates are discussed in Chapter 34.
Specific disorders that are the direct consequence of maternal diseases are discussed in pertinent chapters.
Respiratory Distress.
At the time of delivery, the newborn must convert rapidly to air breathing as described in Chapter 32 (p. 586).
With inspiration, alveoli expand, lung fluid is cleared, and surfactant prevents alveolar collapse.
Interference with these functions can create respiratory insufficiency.
The neonate demonstrates hypoxemia and compensatory tachypnea, nasal flaring, chest wall retractions, and grunting.
In preterm neonates, this is often caused by lung immaturity and insufficient surfactant—respiratory distress syndrome (RDS), which is discussed in Chapter 34 (p. 615).
As fetuses approach term, surfactant deficiency as a cause of respiratory distress diminishes.
The leading causes in term newborns are transient tachypnea of the newborn (TTN), meconium aspiration syndrome, pneumonia, and pneumothorax.
Less common etiologies are RDS, persistent pulmonary hypertension, acid/base disturbances, central nervous system (CNS) insults, and congenital chest, respiratory tract, CNS, or cardiac anomalies .
Following birth, successful neonatal transition to air breathing may be delayed.
With longer delays, evaluations to identify the cause of respiratory distress are warranted.
The initial neonatal evaluation includes chest radiographs.
Complete blood count or C-reactive protein levels and blood cultures are obtained to identify infection.
Arterial blood gas assessments can define respiratory status and direct oxygenation care.
In general, treatment of respiratory distress is supportive with oxygen therapy provided as needed.
Depending on the etiology and severity, continuous positive airway pressure (CPAP) or mechanical ventilation may be needed.
Nutritional intake may be oral, gavage, or intravenous depending on the degree of neonatal tachypnea.
High respiratory rates can limit effective breastfeeding and raise aspiration risk.
# Transient Tachypnea of the Newborn.
TTN is benign, self-limited, and stems from slow clearance of fetal lung fluid after birth.
Neonates of any gestational age can be affected.
However, delivery before 39 weeks’ gestation raises risk, and rates vary inversely with gestational age.
Other risk factors are cesarean delivery without labor, male gender, perinatal asphyxia, and large- or small-for-gestational-age birthweight.
Maternal gestational diabetes or asthma are others.
TTN is a diagnosis of exclusion.
Thus, the evaluation outlined in the last section excludes pathological sources.
Treatment is supportive with oxygen therapy as needed.
Most TTN cases resolve within 48 hours.
# Respiratory Distress Syndrome.
This condition stems from surfactant deficiency and has a relatively low incidence at term .
Risks include male gender, white race, and maternal diabetes (Anadkat, 2012; Li, 2019).
Less frequently, rare mutations in genes that code for surfactant protein synthesis may contribute.
Four are surfactant protein B, surfactant protein C, adenosine triphosphate (ATP)-binding cassette subfamily A member 3 (ABCA3), and thyroid transcription factor 1 genes .
Regardless of etiology, when surfactant secretion is diminished, the pulmonary pathophysiology, clinical course, and management are similar to that for preterm infants.
Treatment includes CPAP or mechanical ventilation and potentially surfactant
replacement either through an endotracheal tube or by less invasive surfactant techniques .
Bacterial pneumonia, especially related to group B Streptococcus in a newborn is often clinically and radiographically indistinguishable from RDS.
Thus, empirical antibiotics are often added to respiratory management.
The prognosis in term newborns with RDS largely depends on the cause, severity, and response to treatment.
Antenatal maternal corticosteroid treatment is employed for threatened preterm birth and described in Chapter 45 (p. 802).
In late-preterm fetuses 34 to 37 weeks’ gestation, this therapy also enhances surfactant synthesis .
At Parkland Hospital, corticosteroids are not given in the late-preterm period for this indication.
Neonatal hypoglycemia is a concern with such treatment, and long-term effects are unknown.
However, data indicate that hypoglycemia, if promptly treated, creates no adverse sequelae .
# Meconium Aspiration Syndrome.
The physiology of meconium passage and amnionic fluid contamination is considered in Chapter 24 (p. 458).
In some instances, inhalation of meconium-stained fluid at or near delivery causes acute airway obstruction, chemical pneumonitis, surfactant dysfunction or inactivation, and pulmonary hypertension .
If severe, hypoxemia may lead to neonatal death or long-term neurological sequelae in survivors.
Meconium-stained fluid in labor is common.
Fortunately, severe aspiration leading to overt respiratory failure is much less frequent.
In one study, the incidence of severe disease was 4 cases per 1000 newborn hospital discharges, and rates rise progressively from 37 to 43 weeks’ gestation .
Mortality rates depend on severity.
Fetal morbidity is more often associated with thicker meconium content.
Presumably, in most cases, amnionic fluid is ample to dilute the meconium to permit prompt clearance by normal fetal physiological mechanisms.
Meconium aspiration syndrome still occasionally develops with light staining.
Many newborns are affected after a normal labor and uncomplicated delivery.
However, some associated obstetrical factors include postterm pregnancy and fetal-growth restriction.
These fetuses are at highest risk because diminished amnionic fluid and labor with cord compression or uteroplacental insufficiency are often comorbid.
These can enhance the likelihood of meconium passage that is thick and undiluted .
Prevention Previously, aspiration was thought to be stimulated by fetal hypoxic episodes, and fetal heart rate tracing abnormalities were used to identify fetuses at greatest risk during labor.
Unfortunately, this was found to be an unreliable predictor .
As another potential prevention, oropharyngeal suctioning at the perineum was standard care for a time.
However, this was abandoned when evidence failed to support a reduction in meconium aspiration syndrome incidence or severity (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021b; Vain, 2004).
From other studies, endotracheal intubation and suctioning for both vigorous and nonvigorous meconium-stained neonates provides no benefit and is no longer recommended as a routine (Trevisanuto, 2020; Wiswell, 2000; Wyckoff, 2020).
Because neonates born through meconium may need effective positive pressure ventilation for stabilization, it is still critical that pediatric providers attend such deliveries .
Intrapartum amnioinfusion has been used successfully in laboring women with diminished amnionic fluid volume to help resolve frequent variable fetal heart rate decelerations .
Earlier, it was also studied as a preventive measure in labors complicated by meconium staining.
This practice fails to lower rates of meconium aspiration syndrome in settings with standard peripartum surveillance .
A trial was conducted with almost 2000 women at 36 weeks’ gestation or later and in whom labor was complicated by thick meconium .
The perinatal death rate with and without amnioinfusion was 0.05 percent in both groups.
Rates of moderate or severe meconium aspiration also were not significantly different in those with (4.4
percent) and without (3.1 percent) amnioinfusion.
Last, cesarean delivery rates were similar—32 versus 29 percent, respectively.
Treatment Ventilatory support including CPAP, intubation, and mechanical ventilation is carried out as needed .
Because some aspects of meconium aspiration syndrome are caused by surfactant deficiency, replacement therapy is beneficial .
In a review of randomized trials, authors found that surfactant replacement may reduce the need for extracorporeal membrane oxygenation (ECMO) but did not lower the mortality rate .
Inhaled corticosteroids may partially ameliorate the severity of meconium aspiration syndrome, but neither inhaled or systemic corticosteroids consistently improve critical outcomes (Garg, 2016; Yeung, 2021).
Newborns with meconium aspiration syndrome and pulmonary hypertension are often treated with inhaled nitric oxide, which reduces rates of death and need for ECMO .
ECMO therapy is reserved for neonates who remain poorly oxygenated despite maximal ventilatory assistance .
The proportion that requires ECMO treatment varies.
From the California Perinatal Quality Care Collaborative, 0.35 percent of more than 5100 cases of meconium aspiration syndrome required ECMO treatment.
The associated mortality rate was 5.3 percent .
Neonatal Encephalopathy And Cerebral.
Palsy.
Few events evoke more apprehension in parents and obstetricians than the specter of “brain injury,” which immediately prompts concerns for disabling cerebral palsy and intellectual disability.
Although most brain disorders or injuries are less profound, history has helped to perpetuate the more dismal outlook.
In his first edition of this textbook, Williams (1903) limited discussions of brain injury to those sustained from birth trauma.
When later editions introduced the concept that asphyxia neonatorum was another cause of cerebral palsy, this too was linked to traumatic birth.
Even as brain damage caused by traumatic delivery became uncommon during the ensuing decades, the belief—albeit erroneous—was that intrapartum events caused most neurological disability.
This was a major reason for the escalating cesarean delivery rate beginning in the 1970s.
Unfortunately, because the genesis of cerebral palsy occurs long before labor in most cases, cesarean delivery did little to mitigate cerebral palsy risks.
Cerebral palsy rates have remained the same for 50 years despite a sixfold rise in cesarean birth rates .
These realizations stimulated scientific investigations to determine the etiopathogenesis of fetal brain disorders, including those leading to cerebral palsy.
Seminal observations, including those of Nelson and Ellenberg (1984, 1985, 1986a), are discussed subsequently.
These investigators are appropriately credited with proving that these neurological disorders are due to complex multifactorial processes caused by a combination of genetic, physiological, environmental, and obstetrical factors.
Importantly, these studies showed that few neurological disorders are associated with peripartum events.
However, continuing international interest was garnered to codify the potential role of intrapartum events.
In 2000, a task force of the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists was appointed to study neonatal encephalopathy and cerebral palsy.
The multispecialty coalition reviewed data and provided criteria to define various neonatal brain disorders.
Their findings were promulgated by the American Academy of Pediatrics and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2003).
Ten years later, a second task force updated the findings .
The 2014 Task Force findings are more circumspect in contrast to the earlier ones.
Specifically, more limitations are cited in identifying cause(s) of peripartum hypoxicischemic encephalopathy (HIE) compared with other etiologies of neonatal encephalopathy.
The 2014 Task Force recommends multidimensional assessment of each affected infant.
They add the caveat that no one strategy is infallible, and thus no single strategy will achieve 100-percent certainty in
attributing a cause to neonatal encephalopathy.
# Neonatal Encephalopathy.
The 2014 Task Force defined neonatal encephalopathy as a syndrome of neurological dysfunction identified in the earliest days of life in neonates born at ≥35 weeks’ gestation.
It is manifested by seizures or subnormal levels of consciousness and is often accompanied by difficulty with initiating and maintaining respiration and by depressed tone and reflexes.
The incidence of encephalopathy has been cited to be 1 to 2 cases per 1000 term liveborn neonates, and it is much more frequent in preterm newborns (Ensing, 2015; Laptook, 2016; Novak, 2018; Ravichandran, 2020).
The 2014 Task Force concluded that many etiologies may lead to encephalopathy and cerebral palsy, however, it focused on HIE and causes that were thought to be incurred intrapartum.
To identify affected infants, a thorough evaluation is necessary and includes maternal history, obstetrical antecedents, intrapartum factors, placental pathology, and newborn course.
These are complemented by laboratory and neuroimaging findings.
Three clinically defined levels categorize encephalopathy.
Mild encephalopathy is characterized by hyperalertness, irritability, jitteriness, and hypertonia and hypotonia.
Moderate encephalopathy shows lethargy, abnormal tone, and occasional seizures.
Severe encephalopathy is manifest by coma, multiple seizures, and recurrent apnea.
The 2014 Task Force also concluded that of the several forms of cerebral palsy, only the spastic quadriplegic type can result from acute peripartum ischemia.
Other forms—hemiparetic or hemiplegic cerebral palsy, spastic diplegia, and ataxia—are unlikely to result from an intrapartum event.
Purely dyskinetic or ataxic cerebral palsy, especially when accompanied by a learning disorder, usually has a genetic origin .
Criteria for Hypoxic-Ischemic Encephalopathy The 2014 Task Force radically revised the 2003 criteria used to define an acute peripartum event that is consistent with HIE and neonatal encephalopathy.
These are outlined in Table 33-1 and are considered with the following caveats .
Table 33-1.
Findings Consistent with an Acute Peripartum or Intrapartum Event Leading to Hypoxic-Ischemic Encephalopathy First, Apgar scores that are low at 5 and 10 minutes are associated with greater risk for neurological impairment.
Low scores stem from many causes, and most of these infants will not develop cerebral palsy.
With a 5-minute Apgar ≥7, it is unlikely that peripartum HIE caused cerebral palsy.
Acid-base study results define a second HIE criterion.
Low pH and high base deficit levels raise the likelihood that neonatal encephalopathy was caused by HIE.
Decreasing pH levels form a continuum of increasing risk, but most acidemic neonates will be neurologically normal .
A cord artery pH ≥7.2 is very unlikely to be associated with HIE.
Magnetic resonance (MR) imaging or MR spectroscopy (MRS) is the best modality with which to visualize findings consistent with HIE.
The 2014 Task Force concluded that cranial sonography and computed tomography (CT) lack sensitivity in the term newborn.
Normal imaging findings after the first 24 hours of life, however, effectively exclude a hypoxic-ischemic cause of encephalopathy.
MR imaging between 24 and 96 hours may be more sensitive for the timing of peripartum cerebral injury, and MR imaging at 7 to 21 days following birth is the best technique to delineate the full extent of cerebral injury.
Last, multisystem involvement of injury is consistent with HIE.
These include renal, gastrointestinal, hepatic, or cardiac injury; hematological abnormalities; or combinations of these.
The severity of neurological injury does not necessarily correlate with injuries to these other systems.
The 2014 Task Force also found that certain contributing factors may be consistent with an acute peripartum event.
Of these, sentinel events are considered adverse obstetrical events that may lead to catastrophic clinical outcomes.
Examples include ruptured uterus, severe placental abruption, cord prolapse, and
amnionic fluid embolism.
Martinez-Biarge and associates (2012) studied almost 58,000 deliveries and identified 192 cases with one of these sentinel events.
Of these 192 fetus/newborns, 6 percent died intrapartum or in the early neonatal period, and 10 percent developed neonatal encephalopathy.
Other risk factors for neonatal acidosis include prior or emergent cesarean delivery, maternal age ≥35 years, maternal obesity, thick meconium, chorioamnionitis, and general anesthesia (Johansson, 2018; Johnson, 2014; Nelson, 2014).
Differentiating an abnormal fetal heart rate (FHR) tracing on presentation versus one that develops subsequently also was emphasized by the 2014 Task Force.
A category 1 or 2 FHR tracing associated with Apgar scores ≥7 at 5 minutes, normal cord gases (±1 SD), or both are not consistent with an acute HIE event .
An FHR pattern at the time of presentation with persistently minimal or absent variability and lacking accelerations, with duration ≥60 minutes, and even without decelerations is suggestive of an already compromised fetus .
The 2014 Task Force further recommended that with these findings present, if fetal well-being cannot be established, the woman should be evaluated for the method and timing of delivery.
Prevention In term newborns, one of the best-studied interventions for neonatal HIE is postnatally induced hypothermia.
Cooling initiated within the first 6 hours of life to a level of 33.5°C for 72 hours reduces death and moderate to severe neurological disability in term newborns (Jacobs, 2013; Natarajan, 2016b).
One metaanalysis of more than 1500 neonates concluded that hypothermia improves survival rates and neurodevelopment by 24 months of age .
This neuroprotection extends to childhood (Azzopardi, 2014; Guillet, 2012; Shankaran, 2012).
MR imaging studies have demonstrated a slowing of diffusional abnormalities and fewer infarctions with hypothermia (Bednarek, 2012; Natarajan, 2016b).
Longer or deeper cooling does not offer additional protection compared with standard cooling .
Importantly, hospitals should develop plans for timely transfer of encephalopathic newborns to a cooling center for evaluation and possible treatment.
A trial of “late” hypothermia, with cooling initiated after 6 hours of life, showed some benefit.
However, brain protection was not as robust as with cooling initiated in the first 6 hours .
Since therapeutic hypothermia is not completely protective, adjuvant therapies are being explored.
In preclinical HIE models, erythropoietin has both early and late beneficial effects.
These include antiapoptosis and antiinflammatory effects and greater neurogenesis, oligodendrogenesis, and angiogenesis .
One metaanalysis of small clinical trials evaluating this therapy for neuroprophylaxis reports some reductions in cognitive impairment and cerebral palsy rates .
A large national trial has completed enrollment and is in the follow-up phase .
Other adjuvant therapies under investigation are allopurinol, xenon, melatonin, and stem cell therapies .
# Cerebral Palsy.
This term refers to a group of nonprogressive disorders of movement or posture caused by abnormal development or damage to brain centers for motor control.
Cerebral palsy is further classified by the type of neurological dysfunction—spastic, dyskinetic, or ataxic—and by the number and distribution of limbs involved—quadriplegia, diplegia, hemiplegia, or monoplegia.
Together, the major types are spastic quadriplegia—the most common—which has a strong association with mental retardation and seizure disorders; diplegia, which is common in preterm or low-birthweight neonates; hemiplegia; choreoathetoid types; and mixed varieties.
Although epilepsy and intellectual disability frequently accompany cerebral palsy, these two disorders seldom are associated with perinatal asphyxia in the absence of cerebral palsy.
Incidence and Epidemiological Correlates According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (2021), the prevalence of cerebral palsy in the United States approximates 3 cases in 1000
children.
It is crucial to emphasize that this rate is derived from all children—including those born preterm.
Because of the remarkably greater survival rates of the latter currently, and despite the elevated cesarean delivery rate, the overall rate of cerebral palsy has remained essentially unchanged .
For example, neonates born at 23 to 27 weeks’ gestation in a Swedish birth cohort had a cerebral palsy incidence of 105 cases per 1000 infants alive at 1 year (Hafström, 2018).
Similar findings have been reported for Australian births .
In absolute numbers, term newborns constitute half of cerebral palsy cases because preterm births are proportionately far fewer.
It is again emphasized that most studies of cerebral palsy rates have not made distinctions between term and preterm neonates.
Figure 33-1.
Elective and emergency cesarean deliveries and live births with cerebral palsy.
Reproduced with permission from Nelson KB, Blair E: Prenatal factors in singletons with cerebral palsy born at or near term, N Engl J Med. 2015 Sep 3;373(10):946–953.
As noted earlier, Nelson and Ellenberg (1984, 1985, 1986a) made many fundamental observations concerning cerebral palsy.
Their initial studies emanated from data from the Collaborative Perinatal Project.
This included children from almost 54,000 pregnancies who were followed until age 7.
They found that the most frequently associated risk factors for cerebral palsy were: (1) evidence of genetic abnormalities such as maternal mental retardation or fetal congenital malformations; (2) birthweight <2000 g; (3) birth before 32 weeks; and (4) perinatal infection.
They also found that obstetrical complications were not strongly predictive, and only a fifth of affected children had markers of perinatal asphyxia.
For the first time, solid evidence supported that the cause of most cases of cerebral palsy was unknown, and importantly, only a small proportion stemmed from neonatal HIE.
Equally importantly, no foreseeable single intervention would likely prevent a large proportion of cases.
Numerous studies have since confirmed many of these findings and have identified an imposing list of other risk factors .
As expected, preterm birth continues to be the single most important risk .
Small-for-gestational-age neonates also are at higher risk.
In one study, cerebral palsy was due to antepartum factors in more than 90 percent of growth-restricted newborns .
Table 33-2.
Perinatal Risk Factors Reported to Be Increased in Children with Cerebral Palsy Many other placental and neonatal risk factors are associated with neurodevelopmental abnormalities .
Some placental factors are discussed further in Chapter 6 (p. 111).
One example is the substantively greater risk from chorioamnionitis (Shevell, 2014; Shi, 2017).
Of neonatal causes, one is arterial ischemic stroke, which may be associated with inherited fetal thrombophilias (Harteman, 2013; Wanenaar, 2018).
Additionally, newborns with isolated congenital heart lesions have an elevated risk for microcephaly, possibly due to chronic fetal hypoxemia .
Other miscellaneous etiologies of cerebral palsy include fetal anemia, twin-twin transfusion syndrome, intrauterine transfusions, and fetal alcohol syndrome (DeJong, 2012; Nelson, 2015; O’Leary, 2012; Rossi, 2011; Schou, 2019).
Apart from these causes, intrapartum hypoxemia was linked to only a few cases of cerebral palsy by the National Collaborative Perinatal Project.
The contribution of HIE to subsequent neurological disorders was discussed earlier.
The 2003 Task Force applied these criteria to more contemporaneous outcomes and determined that only 1.6 cases of cerebral palsy per 10,000 deliveries are attributable solely to intrapartum hypoxia.
This finding is supported by a study of nearly 1000 infants in which fetal-growth restriction and birth defects recognized by age 6 years were more substantial contributors to cerebral palsy and neonatal death than potentially asphyxial birth events and inflammation .
Intrapartum Fetal Heart Rate Monitoring Despite persistent attempts to validate
continuous intrapartum electronic FHR monitoring as effective to prevent adverse perinatal outcomes, evidence does not support its ability to predict or reduce cerebral palsy risk .
Moreover, no specific FHR patterns is predictive of cerebral palsy, and no relationship has been found between the clinician’s response to abnormal patterns and neurological outcome.
Efforts using computer-assisted analysis of FHR tracings have not enhanced predictions (Alfirevic, 2017; INFANT Collaborative Group, 2017).
Indeed, an abnormal heart rate pattern in fetuses that ultimately develop cerebral palsy may reflect a preexisting neurological abnormality .
Because of these studies, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019a; 2021a) concludes that electronic FHR monitoring does not reduce the incidence of long-term neurological impairment.
Apgar Scores In general, 1- and 5-minute Apgar scores are poor predictors of long-term neurological impairment .
However, if the 5-minute Apgar score is ≤3, neonatal death or the risk of neurological sequelae rises substantially (Chen, 2020; Nelson, 1984).
In a Swedish study, 5 percent of such children subsequently required special schooling .
In a Scottish study, the incidence of these low Apgar scores was 0.3 percent in more than 750,000 children who were born at term and were in national school census records.
Low Apgar score was strongly associated in a dose-dependent manner with the need for additional educational support in later life, after adjusting for confounding factors.
The strongest association was for the support of physical and motor impairments and was followed by visual, hearing, and cognitive impairments .
Persistence past 5 minutes of these extremely low scores correlates strongly with a higher risk for neurological morbidity and death .
This of course is not absolute, and the 2003 Task Force cited a 10percent risk for cerebral palsy for neonates with 10-minute scores of 0 to 3.
For 15-minute scores ≤2, the cited mortality rate was 53 percent, and cerebral palsy rate was 36 percent.
For 20-minute scores ≤2, the mortality rate was 60 percent, and cerebral palsy rate was 57 percent.
Outcomes from a Norwegian population study of neonates who were born from low-risk pregnancies and who had low 5-minute Apgar scores are shown in Table 333 .
Table 33-3.
Comparison of Mortality and Morbidity in Norwegian Infants Weighing >2500 g According to 5-Minute Apgar Scores Umbilical Cord Blood Gas Studies Objective evidence of metabolic acidosis, that is, cord arterial blood pH <7.0 and base deficit ≥12 mmol/L, is a risk factor for encephalopathy and for cerebral palsy (p. 601).
The risk accrues as acidosis worsens.
From one review of 51 studies, low pH in arterial umbilical cord blood correlates with greater risk for neonatal encephalopathy and cerebral palsy .
When used alone, however, these determinations are not accurate in predicting long-term neurological sequelae .
Data from several studies corroborate that a pH <7.0 is the threshold for clinically significant acidemia (Gilstrap, 1989; Goldaber, 1991).
The likelihood of neonatal death grows as the cord artery pH falls to ≤7.0.
Casey and colleagues (2001) reported that when the pH was ≤6.8, the neonatal mortality rate rose 1400-fold.
When the cord pH was ≤7.0 and the 5-minute Apgar score was 0 to 3, the risk of neonatal death rose 3200-fold.
In a study from Oxford, the rate of adverse neurological outcomes was 0.36 percent with pH <7.1 and was 3 percent with pH <7.0 .
A systematic review that includes 12 studies suggests that cord blood lactate levels also help predict neonatal outcomes .
Nucleated Red Blood Cells and Lymphocytes Both immature red cells and lymphocytes enter the circulation of term newborns in response to hypoxia or hemorrhage.
During the past two decades, quantification of these cells has been proposed as a measure of hypoxia, but not all studies support this premise (Boskabadi, 2017; Silva, 2006; Walsh, 2011, 2013).
# Neuroimaging Studies in Encephalopathy and Cerebral.
Palsy
Various neuroimaging techniques have provided important insight into the etiology and evolution of perinatal HIE and later cerebral palsy.
Findings vary by fetal age, and the preterm neonatal brain responds differently to an ischemic episode than that of a term newborn.
Other factors include insult severity and duration and restoration of cerebrovascular hypoperfusion.
Thus, precise timing of an injury with neuroimaging studies is not a realistic goal.
Moreover, the grade of neonatal encephalopathy, that is, mild, moderate, or severe, does not correlate with MR imaging findings .
Neuroimaging in the Neonatal Period The 2014 Task Force concluded that for term newborns, imaging studies are helpful in timing an injury, but they provide only a time window that is imprecise.
The 2014 Task Force reported that these head imaging techniques provide the following information: 1. Neonatal sonography findings are generally normal on the day of birth.
With injury, the thalami and basal ganglia become increasingly echogenic beginning at approximately 24 hours.
This progresses over 2 to 3 days and persists for 5 to 7 days.
2. CT images are usually normal the first day in term newborns.
With injury, the thalami or basal ganglia show decreased density beginning at approximately 24 hours, and this persists for 5 to 7 days.
3. MR imaging will detect some abnormalities on the first day.
Within 24 hours, MR imaging may show restricted water diffusion that peaks at approximately 5 days and disappears within 2 weeks.
T1- and T2- weighted images display variable abnormalities, which have an onset from less than 24 hours to several days.
In a study of 175 term neonates with acute encephalopathy, MR imaging that showed basal ganglia lesions accurately predicted motor impairment at 2 years of age .
Neuroimaging in Older Children with Cerebral Palsy Imaging studies performed in children diagnosed with cerebral palsy frequently show abnormal findings.
Wu and associates (2006) used CT or MR imaging to study 273 children who were born after 36 weeks’ gestation and who were later diagnosed with cerebral palsy.
Although a third of these imaging studies were normal, focal arterial infarction was seen in 22 percent; brain malformations in 14 percent; and periventricular white-matter injuries in 12 percent.
In another study of 351 children with cerebral palsy, of whom approximately half were born near term, MR imaging findings were abnormal in 88 percent .
One MR imaging study found pathological findings in 84 percent of children with spastic quadriplegia .
Remember, the 2014 Task Force concluded that this neurological lesion correlated with neonatal encephalopathy.
Imaging techniques in older children also help define the timing of fetal or perinatal cerebral injury.
Due to concerns regarding the radiation exposure of CT scans, MR imaging is more often used.
Wiklund and coworkers (1991a,b) studied 83 children between ages 5 and 16 years who were born at term and who developed hemiplegic cerebral palsy.
Nearly 75 percent had abnormal CT findings, and these investigators concluded that more than half had CT changes that suggested a prenatal injury.
Approximately 20 percent were attributed to a perinatal injury.
# Intellectual Disability and Seizure Disorders.
These both frequently accompany cerebral palsy.
However, when either manifests alone, it is seldom caused by perinatal hypoxia (Nelson, 1984, 1986a, 2015).
Severe mental disability has a prevalence of 3 cases per 1000 children, and its most frequent causes are chromosomal, gene mutation, and other congenital malformations.
Last, preterm birth also is associated with these .
The major predictors of seizure disorders are fetal malformations— cerebral and noncerebral; family history of seizures; and neonatal seizures (Nelson, 1986b; Pisani, 2015).
Neonatal encephalopathy causes a small proportion of seizure disorders.
Reports from the Neonatal Research Network and other studies conclude that increasing severity of encephalopathy correlates best with seizures (Glass, 2011; Kwon, 2011).
Autism
Spectrum Disorders According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, the frequency of autism spectrum disorders is 15 cases per 1000 8-year-old children .
Although these may be associated with maternal metabolic conditions, none has been linked convincingly to peripartum events .
Neonatal Abstinence Syndrome.
This is a drug-withdrawal syndrome that most commonly follows in-utero exposure to maternal opioids.
It also can complicate exposure to alcohol or benzodiazepines.
The syndrome shows hypertonia, autonomic instability, irritability, poor sucking reflex, and seizures .
Its incidence has risen six- to sevenfold during the past decade, coincidental with growing opioid use.
For example, 4 percent of all neonatal intensive care unit days in 2013 were attributed to care of these affected newborns .
Care includes close observation, and pharmacotherapy is usually given.
In addition to morphine and methadone, other treatment may include phenobarbital, benzodiazepines, and clonidine .
More recently, buprenorphine compared with morphine was reported to result in shorter lengths of treatment and hospital stays (Kraft, 2017; Lee, 2019).
Consensus is lacking regarding the most effective regimen.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the American Society of Addiction Medicine (2019c) have taken the lead in screening, intervention, and treatment of opioid use disorders in pregnant women .
Hematological Disorders.
Obstetricians should be familiar with a few neonatal disorders of erythrocytes, platelets, and coagulation.
Many of these manifest in the fetus and persist in the newborn.
# Anemia.
After 35 weeks’ gestation, the mean cord hemoglobin concentration approximates 17 g/dL, and values below 14 g/dL are considered abnormal.
In newborns, delayed umbilical cord clamping raises hemoglobin levels at birth and improves iron stores in the first several months.
A review of nearly 9200 late-preterm and term deliveries found delayed cord clamping was associated with a mean neonatal hemoglobin rise of 1.2 g/dL at birth .
However, rates of infant anemia at 6 months were similar in groups with or without delayed cord clamping.
Moreover, this practice raises the incidence of hyperbilirubinemia that requires phototherapy but does not prolong hospital stay.
Discussed further in Chapter 27 (p. 500), the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020) recommends a 30- to 60-second delay in cord clamping in all healthy newborns.
Significant neonatal anemia may predate or follow delivery.
First, neonatal anemia may reflect an extension of antenatal fetal anemia.
General etiological groups are immune-medicated red cell destruction, aneuploidy, hematology-related genetic defects, fetomaternal hemorrhage, fetal infection, and placental abnormalities such as chorioangioma or twin anastomotic defects.
Second, at delivery, acute anemia with hypovolemia can follow laceration of the placenta, fetal vessel, or umbilical cord.
Intracranial or extracranial injury or trauma to fetal intraabdominal organs also can cause hemorrhage with acute anemia .
# Polycythemia.
Neonatal polycythemia can be associated with chronic or acute fetal hypoxia, twin anemia-polycythemia syndrome, maternal diabetes or hypertension, placental- and fetal-growth restriction, aneuploidy, and delayed cord clamping.
When the hematocrit rises above 65, blood viscosity markedly increases.
Routine neonatal screening is not recommended in newborns without symptoms .
Frequent signs are hypotonia, a ruddy complexion (plethora), respiratory distress with cyanosis, jitteriness, or hypoglycemia.
Because of the shorter life span of macrocytic fetal erythrocytes, hyperbilirubinemia commonly follows.
Associated blood hyperviscosity can lead to end-organ damage and neurodevelopmental harm.
Isovolemic partial exchange transfusion (PET) with saline can lower the hematocrit and improve symptoms, however, it is not neuroprotective and has associated complications .
From limited data, PET is often reserved for neonates with acute symptoms or hypoglycemia .
#
Hyperbilirubinemia.
Excessive serum bilirubin levels can be neurotoxic for newborns.
In fetuses, hepatic maturation is incomplete, and some unconjugated bilirubin is cleared by placental transfer to be conjugated and excreted by the mother.
After delivery, clearance relies on neonatal hepatic function, and thus varying degrees of neonatal hyperbilirubinemia arise.
Even in the mature newborn, serum bilirubin levels usually increase for 3 to 4 days to reach up to 10 mg/dL.
After this, concentrations usually fall rapidly.
In approximately 15 percent of term newborns, bilirubin levels cause jaundice.
Of risks, polycythemia, hemolysis such as from ABO incompatibility or glucose-6phosphate dehydrogenase deficiency, and extravasation of blood such as from a cephalohematoma all raise bilirubin burden.
Decreased bilirubin clearance is seen with prematurity.
With excessive serum bilirubin levels, toxicity has two forms.
Acute bilirubin encephalopathy develops in the first days of life and may cause hypotonia, poor feeding, lethargy, and abnormal auditory-evoked responses.
Immediate recognition and treatment will usually mitigate progressive neurotoxicity.
The chronic form is termed kernicterus.
With this, profound neuronal degeneration follows bilirubin deposition and staining of the basal ganglia and hippocampus.
Survivors have spasticity, muscular incoordination, and varying degrees of mental deficiencies.
Continuing hemolysis is a risk factor for kernicterus (El Houchi, 2017; Vandborg, 2012).
Initial prevention emphasizes effective breastfeeding to avoid neonatal dehydration.
Surveillance for jaundiced skin is recommended at the same time other newborn vital signs are obtained.
Moreover, prior to hospital discharge, universal screening of total serum bilirubin assessment from blood or more commonly by transcutaneous bilirubinometry is done .
The latter is a handheld meter that directs light into the skin and measures the intensity of specific returned wavelengths.
Once diagnosed, various forms of phototherapy are used to treat neonatal hyperbilirubinemia.
These “bili-lights” emit a spectrum of 460 to 490 nm, which augments bilirubin oxidation to enhance its renal clearance and lower serum levels.
Sunlight filtered to remove ultraviolet light can be used in resource-poor countries .
Light that penetrates the skin also raises peripheral blood flow, which further enhances photo-oxidation.
For term newborns, the American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) stress early detection and prompt phototherapy to prevent bilirubin encephalopathy.
Despite these measures, bilirubin encephalopathy persists, and this is somewhat related to early hospital discharges .
In the United States, hospitalizations for kernicterus in term newborns were 5 cases per 100,000 in 1988 .
Since then, this rate has dropped to 0.4 to 2.7 cases per 100,000 births .
Legislation to minimize brief postpartum hospital stays may be contributory .
# Vitamin K Deficiency Bleeding.
Newborns are vitamin K deficient due to insufficient antenatal liver stores, limited synthesis in an initially sterile gut, and low vitamin K content in breast milk.
Vitamin K deficiency bleeding (VKDB) describes spontaneous internal or external bleeding, and its onset is grouped as early, classic, or late onset.
Most cases result from abnormally low levels of the vitamin K– dependent clotting factors.
Early onset is within the first 24 hours, and one cause is maternal vitamin K deficiency.
Classic hemorrhagic disease is usually apparent between days 2 and 7 of life in neonates not given vitamin K prophylaxis at delivery.
Delayed hemorrhage may occur at 2 to 12 weeks in exclusively breastfed infants.
The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) recommend routine prophylaxis with a single, intramuscular, 0.5- to 1-mg dose of vitamin K1 (phytonadione).
Oral administration is less effective, and maternal vitamin K administration results in very little transport to the fetus .
Evidence does not support initial links with vitamin K and childhood leukemia (Fear, 2003; Roman, 2002).
Hemorrhagic disease of the newborn includes VKDB but also bleeding from other etiologies.
These include congenital clotting factor deficiency, disseminated intravascular coagulopathy, birth trauma, and thrombocytopenia.
# Thrombocytopenia.
Abnormally low platelet concentrations in term newborns are often categorized as early onset, within the first 72 hours, and late onset thereafter.
In the term neonate, causes include immune disorders, infections, inherited platelet defects, or congenital syndromes (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019b; Cremer, 2016).
Of immunologic sources, neonatal thrombocytopenia stemming from alloimmunization or from maternal idiopathic thrombocytopenic purpura are described in Chapter 18 (p. 359).
Neonatal lupus syndrome can also show thrombocytopenia .
With all these, antiplatelet IgG transferred to the fetus may cause accelerated platelet destruction.
Alternatively, thrombocytopenia can be an extension of fetal infection with B19 parvovirus, cytomegalovirus, toxoplasmosis, and others discussed in Chapters 67 and 68.
Neonatal thrombocytopenia has been reported with maternal antiretroviral therapy for human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) infection .
Term newborns with sepsis can have accelerated platelet consumption .
Last, inherited platelet disorders are described in Chapter 59 (p. 1059).
Newborn Injuries.
# Incidence.
Birth injury can complicate any term delivery, and from population studies, its incidence approximates 2 percent of deliveries (Linder, 2012; SauberSchatz, 2010).
Imprecision in these numbers may stem from lumping of major and minor injuries and trauma definitions.
In one population study from Washington State, the rate of neonatal birth trauma declined by 14 percent and from 5.3 events per 1000 live births in 2004 to 4.5 in 2013 .
Major injury rates were highest with forceps or vacuum delivery and substantially lower for all caesarean delivery categories.
# Cranial Injuries.
The fetal head has considerable plasticity and can undergo appreciable molding during labor.
However, traumatic head injuries can occur and result in bony fracture or in intracranial or extracranial hemorrhage.
With intra- and extracranial hemorrhages, anatomical location defines their classification .
Table 33-4.
Major Types of Cranial Hemorrhage Intracranial Hemorrhage Most aspects of neonatal intracranial hemorrhage are related to gestational age.
Of the categories shown in Table 33-4, the term newborn may suffer subdural and intracerebral hemorrhages most often.
Intraventricular, subarachnoid, or cerebellar hemorrhages are more frequent in the preterm neonate.
In those born preterm, blood pressure instability, hypoxia, and ischemia are prominent causes and described in Chapter 34 (p. 618).
In term neonates, birth trauma is the most frequent etiology.
Other uncommon causes or contributors include acquired or congenital fetal coagulopathy, vascular anomaly, tumor, genetic mutation, and infection .
Importantly, in some newborns, intracranial hemorrhage may follow an apparently uneventful vaginal delivery, and no cause is found.
Term newborns with intracranial hemorrhage may initially display seizures, apnea or tachypnea, poor feeding, and temperature instability .
Imaging options are sonography or CT, but MR imaging is often preferred.
With most lesions, treatment is supportive and nonsurgical.
However, acute hydrocephalus, rising intracranial pressure, or mass effects are infrequent complications that can prompt surgery .
Names of intracranial lesions reflect anatomy.
First, the meninges forms from the dura, arachnoid, and pia mater, and the dura mater is the external layer.
Subdural hemorrhage collects between the dura and arachnoid mater.
Prolonged and difficult delivery can produce cranial molding, dural stretch, and tearing of bridging veins in the subdural space (Towner, 1999; Hong, 2018).
Asymptomatic subdural hemorrhage can also accompany uneventful vaginal or cesarean
delivery .
In asymptomatic newborns, prognosis is good .
Poorer outcome may attend those with comorbid conditions or lesions .
Less commonly, subarachnoid hemorrhage collects between the arachnoid and pia mater.
Rarely, epidural hemorrhage collects outside the dura mater and beneath the periosteum.
In both these hemorrhage types, risks, mechanisms, and recovery are similar to subdural hemorrhage (Hong, 2018; Shah, 2016).
Intraventricular hemorrhage is less common in term than preterm newborns.
Described in Chapter 34 (p. 618), the vascular germinal matrix is a vulnerable site for preterm neonates but has mainly regressed by term.
Instead, the choroid plexus, thalamus, or residual germinal matrix are bleeding sources at term.
Etiology can include birth trauma, hypoxia, or coagulation dysfunction.
Additional rare causes are listed in this section’s first paragraph.
However, in small case series, one to two thirds had no identified antecedent (Roland, 1990; Wu, 2003).
Prognosis varies, and worse outcomes are associated with advanced hemorrhage grade or thalamic hemorrhage .
Intracerebral hemorrhage or neonatal hemorrhagic stroke is uncommon at term.
Risk factors are coagulation defects, vascular anomalies, and intrapartum factors that include FHR abnormalities and low Apgar scores.
Trauma is less often implicated .
Intracerebellar hemorrhage is infrequent in the term newborn.
In one series, associated factors were FHR abnormalities, operative vaginal delivery, emergent cesarean delivery, and delivery-room resuscitation .
Prognosis with both intracerebral and intracerebellar hemorrhages is affected by lesion size, presence of additional hemorrhage sites, and associated hydrocephalus or elevated intracranial pressure.
Extracranial Hemorrhage These blood collections accumulate outside the calvarium .
From its most superficial surface inward, the scalp consists of skin, subcutaneous tissue, galea aponeurotica, subgaleal space, and calvarium periosteum .
The galea aponeurotica is dense fibrous tissue, whereas the subgaleal space contains loose, fibroareolar tissue.
Traversing across the subgaleal space are emissary veins, which connect the dural sinuses inside the skull with superficial scalp veins.
Figure 33-2.
Schematic of extracranial lesions in the neonate that include caput succedaneum, subgaleal hemorrhage, and cephalohematoma.
Caput succedaneum is soft-tissue edema of the scalp.
It forms from repetitive contractions that press the head against an unyielding cervix.
The caput is maximal at birth, rapidly grows smaller, and usually disappears within hours or days.
Cephalohematoma is a cranial subperiosteal hematoma.
It has an incidence of 1 percent and makes up a large percentage of birth injuries (Werner, 2011; Kekki, 2020).
It usually develops in the setting of dystocia or operative vaginal delivery.
Vacuum-assisted births have a greater association than births by forceps or cesarean delivery (Alexander, 2006; Werner, 2011).
Cephalohematoma develops from shearing forces during labor and delivery, which lacerate the emissary or diploic veins.
Fortunately, the densely adhered periosteum impedes rapid enlargement and limits final hematoma size.
Hemorrhage can be over one or both parietal bones, but collections do not cross suture lines.
A cephalohematoma may not be apparent until hours after delivery, when bleeding is sufficient to raise the periosteum.
After it is identified, it often grows larger and persists for weeks or even months, and bleeding may cause anemia or hyperbilirubinemia.
Outcomes are good in the absence of additional injuries.
Rare hematoma complications are infection or calcification (Kandemirli, 2020; Zimmermann, 2016).
Subgaleal hemorrhage is rare and results from emissary vein laceration and bleeding between the galea aponeurotica and the skull periosteum.
Both the galea aponeurotica and subgaleal space span across the occipital, parietal, and frontal bones.
Because of its loose areolar tissue and large surface area, significant blood volumes can collect in this potential space and may extend from
the neck to the orbits and laterally to the temporal fascia above the ears .
Resulting hypovolemia can lead to shock and significant morbidity, and cited mortality rates approximate 15 percent (El Dib, 2019; Lee, 2018; Swanson, 2011).
Other findings are seizures, enlarging head circumference, and respiratory distress.
The subgaleal hemorrhage rate is 0.05 percent with spontaneous birth but is ten times greater with vacuum-assisted delivery .
The most frequent associate is operative vaginal delivery, especially with vacuum devices, but cases can follow spontaneous vaginal or cesarean delivery .
In general, diagnosis of extracranial lesions begins with head ultrasound .
This may be sufficient for cephalohematomas.
CT or MR imaging may benefit those with subgaleal hemorrhage to exclude comorbid cranial injuries.
Skull Fractures These are rare but are especially worrisome because of their association with intracranial hemorrhage.
The incidence of birth-related skull fractures approximates 1 case per 100,000 births (Högberg, 2020).
Operative vaginal delivery is an associated factor .
However, cases can also attend spontaneous or cesarean delivery (Dolivet, 2018; Merhar, 2016).
In these, fracture may result from tight skull compression against the bony pelvis, by hand pressure used by the surgeon to lift the head at cesarean delivery, or from transvaginally applied upward hand pressure by an assistant.
Fractures are diagnosed with radiographs or CT. Depending on type, a fracture may be managed expectantly or require surgery.
Prognosis is mainly influenced by comorbid intra- or extracranial injuries.
Figure 33-3.
Depressed skull fracture evident immediately after cesarean delivery.
Labor had progressed, and the head was deep in the pelvis.
Dislodgment of the head from the birth canal was performed by an assistant using manual pressure upward through the vagina.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Kimberly M. Spoonts.) # Spinal Cord Injury.
Overstretch of the spinal cord and its associated hemorrhage and edema are rare.
The cervical spine is most often injured, and excessive traction, rotation, or hyperextension during shoulder dystocia manipulations, breech vaginal delivery, and operative vaginal delivery are implicated (Lee, 2020a; Menticoglou, 1995).
Upper cervical spinal cord injury is often fatal, and survivors can be quadriplegic .
Immediate treatment has included ventilator support coupled with corticosteroids or therapeutic hypothermia.
# Peripheral Nerve Injuries.
Brachial Plexopathy Injury can involve a single nerve or can affect a nerve root, plexus, or trunk.
Trauma to the brachial plexus is infrequent.
In one database study, the rate was 1 case per 1000 term births in the United States.
The incidence was 1.3 per 1000 vaginal deliveries and 0.2 per 1000 cesarean deliveries .
Shoulder dystocia, labor dystocia, and breech delivery are risks .
With plexopathy, the injury damages the nerve roots that supply the brachial plexus—C5–8 and T1.
With hemorrhage and edema, axonal function may be temporarily impaired, but the recovery chances are good.
However, with avulsion, the prognosis for complete recovery is poor.
Damage to the C5–6 nerve roots can cause Erb palsy.
Injuries with breech delivery are normally of this type, whereas the more extensive and persistent lesions can follow difficult cephalic deliveries.
The latter are more often forceps or vacuum-assisted vaginal deliveries .
The C5–6 roots join to form the upper trunk of the plexus, and injury leads to paralysis of the deltoid, infraspinatus, and flexor muscles of the forearm.
The affected arm is held straight and internally rotated, the elbow is extended, and the wrist and fingers flexed.
Finger function usually is retained.
Damage to the C8-T1 roots supplying the lower plexus results in Klumpke palsy, in which the hand is flaccid.
With total involvement of all brachial plexus nerve roots, flaccidity of the arm and hand results.
Rarely, with severe injury, phrenic nerve damage can cause ipsilateral diaphragm paralysis, or injury to sympathetic nerve
fibers can cause Horner syndrome, which manifests as ptosis, miosis, and anhidrosis .
Clavicle or humeral fracture can be comorbid, and clinical concern may prompt chest radiography.
MR imaging may be obtained with concern for nerve avulsion .
Because of the importance of brachial plexopathy, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2014b) convened a task force to review extant studies.
This Task Force concluded that shoulder dystocia cannot be accurately predicted, but in most cases, axonal death does not occur and the prognosis is good.
Lindqvist and associates (2012) reported complete recovery in 86 percent of children with C5–6 trauma, which was the most common injury, and in 38 percent of those with C5–7 damage.
However, those with global C5–8–T1 injuries always had permanent disability.
Early physical therapy is initiated to prevent contractures or joint deformity.
Maintaining passive joint motion, promoting extremity use, strengthening affected muscles, and providing compensatory techniques are goals .
Severe injuries may require surgical exploration and nerve reconstruction, usually at 3 to 6 months (Vuillermin, 2016; Wilson, 2016).
Facial Paralysis The facial nerve can be injured as it emerges from the stylomastoid foramen, and this may cause facial paralysis .
From one series, the incidence was 0.3 cases per 1000 term births .
Of these vaginal births, forceps were used in one fourth, and three fourths followed spontaneous birth.
Pressure from the forceps blade or the bony pelvis, respectively, are suggested injury mechanisms.
It can follow cesarean delivery .
Spontaneous recovery within a few days is the rule, however, permanent paralysis has been described .
Figure 33-4.
Left facial nerve injury.
Classically, the eye fails to close tightly, the labionasal fold is lost, and the mouth pulls to the unaffected side during crying.
This was almost completely resolved two days after delivery.
# Fractures.
Most long-bone fractures follow difficult deliveries, however, this is not always the case.
At minimum, palpation of the clavicles and long bones is indicated for all newborns after a difficult delivery.
Overlying crepitation or irregularity will prompt radiography.
Clavicular fractures are common, unpredictable, and una-voidable complications of normal birth (Ahn, 2015; Roberts, 1995).
Their incidence approximates 5 cases in 1000 live births (Kekki, 2020; Linder, 2012).
Rates are tenfold higher with vaginal birth than with cesarean delivery .
With vaginal birth, shoulder dystocia is an association (Högberg, 2020).
With cesarean delivery, greater birth weight is a factor .
Humeral fractures and femoral fractures are rare.
For the humerus, associated settings are breech delivery or posterior arm delivery during shoulder dystocia release (Rietberg, 2003; von Heideken, 2020).
Those of the femur are usually associated with breech presentation.
Because most breech-presenting fetuses now undergo cesarean delivery, most of these fractures are associated with this mode .
As potential prevention for both fracture types, careful splinting of the bone along its long axis and avoiding perpendicular forces during extraction are encouraged.
Last, rib fractures are rare at term.
In one series, none was associated with cardiopulmonary resuscitation (Högberg, 2020).
Instead, compression forces to the chest during difficult birth or shoulder dystocia are implicated (van Rijn, 2009).
# Soft Tissue Injury.
Conceivably, any fetal organ or part could be injured with either vaginal or cesarean delivery.
Intraabdominal hemorrhage is rare and most often stems from the liver, spleen, or adrenal glands, which are disproportionally large in the newborn.
Risks are difficult delivery, especially those presenting breech; cardiac resuscitation; macrosomia; or pathologic enlargement of the involved organ .
Retroperitoneal bleeding with these may manifest as bruising of the flanks, umbilicus, groin, upper thigh, or scrotum (Akin 2011; Heyman, 2011; Raveenthiran, 2008).
Pale skin, distended abdomen, and falling hematocrit
reflect associated hypovolemia.
Treatment involves hemodynamic resuscitation and control of bleeding.
# Congenital Deformity Injuries.
In congenital torticollis, one sternocleidomastoid muscle fails to elongate sufficiently.
The head gradually turns toward the side of the injury.
Its etiology is unclear.
Some cases are associated with breech presentation, operative vaginal birth, or difficult delivery.
However, many follow uncomplicated birth, and intrauterine positioning, genetics, and ischemia are some suggested theories (Hardgrib, 2017; Sargent, 2019).
Early physical therapy is recommended .
With congenital deformations, a normally developed fetal structure becomes deformed usually by restrictive intrauterine mechanical forces.
Common factors are chronic oligohydramnios, multifetal gestation, or abnormally shaped or small uterine cavity.
Some mechanical deformations include talipes equinovarus (clubfoot) and oligohydramnios sequence (Hall, 2014; Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine, 2019).
The latter may lead to pulmonary hypoplasia and deformations of the head, face, skin, and limbs.
This sequence and talipes can also be associated with genetic abnormalities or malformations and are discussed in Chapters 14 and 15 (p. 260 and 303).
Last, congenital hip dislocation is strongly associated with an in-utero breech presentation .
Physical examination screening for all newborns is recommended.
Treatment may include observation or bracing .